What's up preppies?
Welcome back to our writing course.
After brainstorming and making an outline with all the ideas that are
well connected, the next step is to form sentences and paragraphs from
those ideas.
And importantly, between those sentences and paragraphs, we need to use
cohesive devices to maintain the cohesion throughout the essay and clearly show
the function and purpose of each sentence and paragraph.
So what are cohesive devices?
Let's choose all the correct answers to the following question.
Question 1.
What do cohesive devices include?
A.
Linking words B.
Sequencing words C.
Number D.
Symbols or E.
Referencing and substitutions The
correct answers are A, B, and E.
Cohesive devices include linking words, sequencing words, and referencing and
substitutions.
To ensure a band 6.0 or higher for cohesion, you should
follow these three steps.
Step 1.
Consider the relationship between two main ideas, then choose the appropriate
cohesive device.
Step 2.
Use appropriate cohesive devices based on the purpose of each sentence.
And Step 3.
Identify if referencing and substitutions are used in sentences of each
paragraph.
If not, add them.
In this video, we will focus specifically on linking devices that you
can use to improve coherence in your IELTS writing.
These linking devices can be categorized by the logical relationships between
ideas or paragraphs in your essay.
The first group is addition.
The linkers in this group are used to expand your argument, or
in other words, to add new ideas that support your previous ones.
You can use furthermore, moreover, in addition or additionally.
For example, our thesis statement is Investing in local tourism brings about many benefits.
The topic sentence of paragraph 1, tourism provides a significant boost to
the local economy.
And the topic sentence of paragraph 2, additionally, it encourages the
preservation of local traditions which might otherwise be lost.
In this example, both paragraphs discuss the benefits of investing in local tourism.
And paragraph 2 adds another idea that supports this.
So we use a linking device for addition.
One note is that furthermore and moreover are best for adding a more persuasive or serious point.
The second group is linking devices for a contrast.
These include however, nevertheless, nonetheless, on the contrary, or in contrast.
These are used to connect two or more ideas that contradict each other.
You will commonly find them in essays discussing both views or advantages and disadvantages.
Let's look at the following example.
Paragraph 1 starts with Tourism provides a significant boost to the local economy.
And paragraph 2, however, critics argue that the government should not
prioritize tourism over essential public services like health care and
education, as the benefits of travel are often seasonal and unreliable.
In this example, the two paragraphs discuss two contradicting ideas.
The first one talks about the benefits of investing in local tourism,
while the second paragraph talks about why the government should not do it.
The third group of linking devices is cause, effect, and result.
These linking devices are commonly used within body paragraph sentences, where
you provide further details and explanation to your topic sentences.
They include, therefore, consequently, as a result, thus, and hence.
One note is that thus and hence are very formal and are
usually followed by a noun or a gerund.
For example, social media has made remote destinations famous.
As a result, these fragile ecosystems face overcrowding.
As you can see, the second idea happens because of the first idea.
So as a result, or other linkers in this group properly connect the two ideas.
Now let's practice using these linking devices in a sample writing.
Your job is to fill in the gaps using the linking devices we just studied.
Look closely at whether the next sentence adds a point, contrasts a
point, or shows a result.
Here is the writing.
I will give you 30 seconds to read and think before answering
the questions, but feel free to pause the video if you need more time.
Now let's look at the answers.
For number one, the answer is furthermore or in addition.
We use these because we are adding a second benefit.
First we mentioned infrastructure and now we are adding the benefit of new roads for local people.
For number two, we use consequently or as a result.
This is because increased mobility happens because of the new roads.
The second sentence is the direct result of the first.
For number three, we must use however.
This is a new paragraph that introduces a contradicting idea.
We are shifting from the pros or benefits in paragraph one to
the cons or drawbacks in paragraph two.
For number four, the answer is therefore or thus.
We use these to show a logical conclusion.
Since tourism changes quickly, the final result for the economy is instability.
Nice job everyone!
So in this video, we have learned about the common linking devices
that you can use in your essays to connect ideas based on
the logical relationships between them.
Let's look at the summary table.
Take notes of the linking devices we learned and remember these three rules.
One, the comma rule.
Always follow these linkers with a comma when they start a sentence.
Two, avoid over linking.
If you start every sentence with the linker, your writing sounds robotic.
Only use them when the logic needs a clear signal.
Three, logic check.
Always check if the linking devices sound logical instead of using them
to show off your vocabulary.
Mastering these three groups is your shortcut to a higher band score
for cohesion.
Remember to practice writing more and more to improve your scores.
Now, goodbye and see you in the next lesson.
See you!